A Guide to the Staunton (Va.) Commonwealth Causes and Criminal Papers, 1807-1919
Library of Virginia
Library of Virginia
Staunton (Va.) Commonwealth Causes and Criminal Papers, 1807-1919
The Library of Virginia
1184512-1184541
10 cu. ft. (30 boxes)
Staunton (Va.) Circuit Court.
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
There are no restrictions.
Acquisition Information
These items came to the Library of Virginia in transfers of court papers from Staunton under the accession number 43238. The microfilm was generated by Backstage Library Works through the Library of Virginia's Circuit Court Records Preservation Program.
Historical Information
The city of Staunton is located in Augusta County. Established as a town in 1761, it was incorporated as a town in 1801 and as an city in 1871. It is one of Virginia's independent cities and therefore functions administratively separately from the county in which it is located.
Scope and Content
Staunton (Va.) Commonwealth Causes and Criminal Papers, 1807-1919, are criminal court cases and other criminal papers that consist primarily of warrants, summons, subpoenas, indictments, recognizances, and verdicts handed down by grand juries and other legal authorities in order to prosecute individuals who violated the penal code. These offenses ranged in severity from murder, rape, assault and battery, and larceny to tax evasion, slander, liquor law violations, prostitution, and contempt of court. Criminal offenders and victims who appear in cases prior to the abolition of slavery in Virginia in 1865 included both free and enslaved persons.
Warrants were issued by grand juries, judges, and justices of the peace directing law enforcement officials to either arrest and imprison a person suspected of having committed a crime or to cause an individual to appear in court to answer accusations made against them. Peace warrants directing an offender to keep the peace of the Commonwealth or to restrain from any violent acts are commonly found in assault and battery cases.
Summonses were used to call a suspected person to appear in court. A summons could also be issued to direct witnesses or victims to come before the court in order to provide evidence or information deemed pertinent to a case. Subpoenas were also used to order witnesses to court to give evidence.
An indictment is the official, written description of the crime that an accused individual is suspected of committing, which is approved by a grand jury and presented to a court in order to begin legal proceedings. Due to this process, indictments are often referred to as presentments.
Verdicts are the formal pronouncements made by juries on issues submitted to them by a judge or other law enforcement official. In the case of a guilty verdict, a judge will sentence the offender. Sentences may include a fine, corporal punishment, and/or imprisonment.
Recognizances were bonds or obligations made in court by which a person promised to do a certain thing such as keep the peace or to appear when called. They are common in assault and battery cases. Often they functioned as a bail bond that guaranteed an unjailed criminal defendant's return for a court date.
Overseers of the Poor causes consist of prosecutions for bastardy or summons to show cause why a child should not be bound out as an apprentice or why an apprenticeship bond should not be broken.
Certificates of justice were notices sent by the jailer that he had committed a certain person or persons to the jail to await trial or other court action.
Arrangement
Arranged by ended court date then alphabetically by defendant surname.
Index Terms
Corporate Names:
Staunton (Va.) Circuit Court.
Subjects:
African Americans -- Virginia -- Staunton.; Apprentices -- Virginia -- Staunton.; Assault and battery -- Virginia -- Staunton.; Contempt of court -- Virginia -- Staunton.; Crime -- Virginia -- Staunton.; Criminals -- Virginia -- Staunton.; Forgery -- Virginia -- Staunton.; Illegitimacy -- Virginia -- Staunton.; Larceny -- Virginia -- Staunton.; Libel and slander -- Virginia -- Staunton.; Liquor laws -- Virginia -- Staunton.; Murder -- Virginia -- Staunton.; Prostitution -- Virginia -- Staunton.; Rape -- Virginia -- Staunton.; Slaveholders -- Virginia -- Staunton.; Slaves -- Virginia -- Staunton.; Tax evasion. -- Virginia -- Staunton.
Geographical Names:
Staunton (Va.) -- History.
Genre and Form Terms:
Indictments -- Virginia -- Staunton.; Local government records -- Virginia -- Staunton.; Subpoenas -- Virginia -- Staunton.; Summons -- Virginia -- Staunton.; Verdicts -- Virginia -- Staunton.; Warrants -- Virginia -- Staunton.
Added Entry - Corporate Name:
Staunton (Va.) Corporation Court.; Staunton (Va.) Hustings Court.
Commonwealth Causes of Interest
- 1808 September, Abraham:
  slave going at large and hiring himself out
- 1812 March, Isaac Collett:
  printing a false and scandalous libel
- 1812 March, John G. Flack:
  uttering opprobrious words to a justice of the peace
- 1814 March, David Phillips:
  fornication with a female slave
- 1817 November, Charles Bankhead:
  sending a challenge to fight a duel
- 1818 March, Washington Doake:
  refuse to help constable take a slave to the whipping post
- 1820 November, Sally Bush, free negro:
  being at an unlawful meeting with slaves
- 1823 August, Lavinia Hewlett and others:
  for not registering as free negroes
- 1828 May, William Carroll Sr.:
  habitual intoxication, abuse of his family and obscene language
- 1829 November, many free negroes:
- 1833 July, John H. Ast:
  public nuisance: slaughterhouse
- 1837 April, Erasmus Stribling, clerk of court:
  permit his slaves to trade as free persons
- 1843 February, Harman J. Lushbaugh:
  obscene graffiti
- 1849 September, Eli Smith, free negro:
  use provoking language to a white man
- 1857 July, Thomas O'Connell and wife:
  permit unlawful assembly of slaves, trade with slaves, sell liquor to slaves
- 1860 February, Samuel Cooper:
  publicly exposing his private parts
- 1860 July, Michael Carmody:
  playing at bagatelle
- 1860 July, James Edwards:
  assemble with negroes in the night time
- 1860 July, Howard Grove and Margaret Sinclair:
  lewd and lascivious cohabitation
- 1863 June, Bridget McCarty alias Bolin:
  received goods stolen from Confederate States government
- 1863 December, George Pforr:
  attempted rape of his daughter
- 1868 February, Thomas Harris:
  rape of multiple children under 12 years of age
- 1882 March, Margaret alias Mag Lewis:
  keep house of ill fame
- 1882 May, Love Smith:
  buggery with a mare
- 1884 September, Crawford and Lalley:
  sell liquor on an election day
- 1884 December, David Kayser:
  public nuisance: backhouse and privy
- 1886 February, John Harris:
  seduction under promise of marriage
- 1887 July, Demetta alias Doctor alias Duretta Liverpool:
- 1889 March, Nettie Mays alias Fox:
  extortion and blackmail
- 1893 December, W. L. Oliver:
  exhibit semi-nude photograph in his window
- 1894 March, Preston Moon:
  seduction
- 1899 March, John T. Todd:
  abduction with the intent to deitem
- 1901 January, N. C. Watts, jailer:
  permitting the escape of a prisoner from the county jail
- 1901 September, Horace Miller:
  house burning
- 1906 February, Kemp Howdyshell:
  escape from jail
- 1906 May, David M. Kyle:
  murder
- 1908 September, Canary Morris:
  possession of cocaine with the intent to sell; selling cocaine
- 1908 October, Albert Spiers:
  attempted murder
- 1909 July, Walter D. Hoge:
  illegal voting
- 1916 December, Edward Bryant:
  buggery with a child
- 1917 September, John H. Johnson:
  bigamy